Guide to the William Sloane Coffin, Jr. Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Audiovisual Material
  - Coffin, William Sloane
    - Untitled sermon on Matthew 12, Undated
      - Use copy cassette (Box 59U)
    - Untitled speech to high school seniors [re: "walking on water" passage in book of Matthew], Undated
      - Original [reel-to-reel; restricted] (Box 60)
      - Duplicating master [reel-to-reel; restricted] (Box 60-D)
      - Use copy cassette (Box 60U)
    - Untitled sermon on commencement day, Undated (Box 61)
    - Untitled sermon re: freedom, Undated (Box 62)
  - Recordings of others
    - Ahlstrom, Sidney. "A History of Yale and the Church: The Great Awakening", Undated
      - Original [two reel-to-reel tapes; restricted (Box 63)
      - Duplicating master [reel-to-reel; restricted] (Box 63-D)
      - Use copy cassette (Box 63U)
    - Concerned Citizens. "Human Beings Fused Together", 1970s (Box 64)
    - Hertzburg, Arthur. "Jewish and Christian Identity in the Secular World", Undated (Box 65)
    - Lovett, Sidney. Talk for Lenten series at Yale University with an introduction by Coffin, 1965 March 28 (Box 66)
    - "The Homosexual and the Church." Panel discussion with Bill Johnson, Susan Day, Henri Nouwen, and Jim Dittes, Undated; audiocassette (Box 67)
      - Duplicating masters, 1; and 1 computer file (wav) (Box 67-D)
      - Use copies, 1; and 1 compact disc (CD-R); audiocassette (Box 67U1–67U2)
    - Unidentified sermon at Battell Chapel on II Corinthians 12:9, Undated
      - Original [reel-to-reel; restricted] (Box 68)
      - Duplicating master [reel-to-reel; restricted] (Box 68-D)
      - Use copy cassette (Box 68U)
    - Riverside Church Disarmament Program, "Waging War in the Nuclear Age Conference", 1987 October 16-17
      - Afghanistan: Superpowers Come Close (Eqbal Ahmad)-Tape I [original cassette; restricted] (Box 69)
      - Afghanistan: Superpowers Come Close (Eqbal Ahmad)-Tape II [original cassette; restricted] (Box 70)
      - Central America: Democracy/Intervention (Eva Gold and Ralph McGehee)-Tape I [original cassette; restricted] (Box 71)
      - Central America: Democracy/Intervention (Eva Gold and Ralph McGehee)-Tape II [original cassette; restricted] (Box 72)
      - Continuing War in Cambodia (Nayan Chanda, Elsie Spivak, and C. Song) [original cassette; restricted] (Box 73)
      - Contras/Every Continent (Eqbal Ahad, Nayan Chanda, Martha Honey, Ralph McGehee, and Stephanie Urdang) [original cassette; restricted] (Box 74)
      - Destabilization in Southern Africa (Stoney Cooks and Cherri Waters)-Tape I [original cassette; restricted] (Box 75)
      - Destabilization in Southern Africa (Stoney Cooks and Cherri Waters)-Tape II [original cassette; restricted] (Box 76)
      - Dictators and Revolutions (Roy Bonner and Sara Miles) [original cassette; restricted] (Box 77)
      - Diplomatic Alternatives (W. Goodfellow); Local Level (Agran, Messinger) [original cassette; restricted] (Box 78)
      - Economic Warfare and Human Rights (Susan George) [original cassette; restricted] (Box 79)
      - Evening for Peace-Part I (Chacabuco, William Sloane Coffin, C. Weiss) [original cassette; restricted] (Box 80)
      - Evening for Peace-Part II (Michael Manley) [original cassette; restricted] (Box 81)
      - Forging Peace in Central America (N. Herrera and Robert Stark) [original cassette; restricted] (Box 82)
      - Keep Your Eyes on the Prize (Roger Wilkins) [original cassette; restricted] (Box 83)
      - Low Intensity Conflict (Michael Klare); From Life Unto Debt (Susan George) [original cassette; restricted] (Box 84)
      - Making Policy at Local Level (Larry Agran and Michael Shulman) [original cassette; restricted] (Box 85)
      - Middle East: Confrontation or Cooperation (D. Kass and Rasheed Khalidi)-Tape I [original cassette; restricted] (Box 86)
      - Middle East: Confrontation or Cooperation (D. Kass and Rasheed Khalidi)-Tape II [original cassette; restricted] (Box 87)
      - Nuclear Weapons: Democracy and Independence (Lyuba Zarsky) [original cassette; restricted] (Box 88)
      - Peace Through Congress? (David Cortright and Carolyn Cottom) [original cassette; restricted] (Box 89)
      - Private Wars/Public Policy (Martha Honey, Dennis Bernstein, C. Blitt, and Robert Knight) [original cassette; restricted] (Box 90)
      - Religion's Role in Foreign Policy (Frances Kennedy and Will Kennedy) [original cassette; restricted] (Box 91)
      - The Selling of War (Amy Goodman and James Ridgeway) [original cassette; restricted] (Box 92)
      - Strategies for Local Organizing (Andrea Ayvazian) [original cassette; restricted] (Box 93)
      - Strategies for a Just Peace (Noam Chomsky, Cesar Jerez, and Major Owens) [original cassette; restricted] (Box 94)
      - Vietnam: What We've Learned-Part I (Gabriel Kolko) [original cassette; restricted] (Box 95)
      - Vietnam: What We've Learned-Part II (Michael Klare, Nelvin Long, and Marilyn Young)-Tape I [original cassette; restricted] (Box 96)
      - Vietnam: What We've Learned-Part III (Michael Klare, Nelvin Long, and Marilyn Young)-Tape II [original cassette; restricted] (Box 97)
    - William Sloane Coffin, Jr. interviewed on The David Susskind Show, [commercially produced], Circa 1975
      - Original, circa 1975; videotape (U-matic) (Box 98)
      - Duplicating master, computer files (DVD-Video)
        Contact Public Services (phone: 203 432-1735, e-mail: mssa.reference@yale.edu) for information on accessing this digital object.
      - Use copy, optical disk (DVD) (Box 98U)
- Additional Material, Accession 2003-M-070
  The accession includes a master, duplicating master, and use copy videotape recording of a talk given by Coffin at the Yale University Library on February 24, 2003. The title of the talk, "War is a Coward's Escape from the Problems of Peace" was derived from a quote by Thomas Mann. The talk was given in support of a library exhibit on the antiwar movement that featured Coffin's papers. Coffin gives his perspective on the upcoming war in Iraq and reflects on his experiences in the antiwar movement in the 1960s.
  - "War is a Coward's Escape from the Problems of Peace" [talk at Sterling Memorial Library ], 2003 February 24
    - Original, videotape (VHS) (Box 1)
    - Duplicating master, videotape (VHS) (Box 1-D)
    - Use copy, videotape (VHS) (Box 1U1)
    - Use copy, videotape (VHS) (Box 1U2)
- Additional Material, 1918-1996; Accession 2004-M-009
  The accession is arranged in four sections: Correspondence; Printed materials and clippings; Topical; and Writings. The materials supplement the main accession and add significant documentation on Coffin's years as senior minister of Riverside Church. Highlighted in the materials is an extensive collection of sermons, both from Riverside and Yale University's Battell Chapel. Though donated by Coffin, these materials were transferred to Yale after the original accession by Warren Goldstein, who used them in researching his biography of Coffin.
  Correspondence is divided into two subsections: general and public opinion mail. General correspondence is arranged chronologically and contains both professional and personal materials. Public opinion mail regarding Vietnam and the freedom ride supplements material in the main accession. Correspondence also contains one folder of unidentified correspondence, mainly written in Russian.
  Printed materials and clippings are arranged chronologically and contain primarily articles about Coffin.
  Arranged alphabetically, Topical files consist of correspondence, clippings, writings, and other materials on particular subjects. Coffin's anti-war activities are documented in nine folders filed under the heading Vietnam War, as well as in files on Americans for Reappraisal of Far Eastern Policy, Amnesty, Capitol rotunda sit-in, Clergy and Laymen Concerned, and the Boston 5 trial. The Boston 5 trial is particularly well documented with clippings, some correspondence, and substantial amounts of legal materials. Topical files also cover Coffin's years as senior minister of Riverside Church and document several causes he fought for while at Riverside. Materials on these subjects can be found in folders under the headings of Riverside Church, Central America, Disarmament, Homosexuality, Iran, Iran-Contra scandal, and South Africa. The accession also contains a small amount of SANE/FREEZE material, which include printed matter, public statements, minutes of meetings, and other professional materials. The SANE/FREEZE materials also include three folders of correspondence congratulating Coffin on becoming president of the organization.
  The Writings comprise the largest part of the accession and are divided into nine subsections: Books; Essays and articles; Interviews; Notes; Prayers; Quotations; Sermons; Speeches; and Writings by others. Books includes manuscript drafts from The Courage to Love and Once to Every Man and edited, printed pages from Living the Truth in a World of Illusions. The vast majority of the subsection consists of multiple drafts of Once to Every Man, which supplement materials found in the main accession.
  Essays and articles date to the Yale and Riverside years and consist of Coffin's publications and manuscripts of published and unpublished works. Where known, the publication in which the articles appeared has been noted. These writings cover a variety of Coffin's main interests, including civil rights, the Vietnam War, and disarmament. Interviews is comprised of the transcripts from nine interviews dating between 1959 and 1996 and are arranged chronologically. The accession also contains a large number of Coffin's Prayers, mainly from the Yale years. The majority of prayers are divided between dated and undated, but where the original folder distinguished specific types of prayers, that distinction has been maintained with separate folder headings.
  Sermons and Speeches comprise the largest two sub-sections of Writings and the division between them is somewhat artificial. When the document itself gave no differentiation, the tendency has been to place the item in speeches rather than sermons. Sermons comprise the majority of the writings and they are arranged chronologically and are subdivided based on Coffin's primary occupation at the time. The accession has only three sermons from Andover and Williams, but contains many sermons from Yale, and nearly every Coffin sermon at Riverside between 1980 and 1986, with a still substantial number of sermons from his other years there. Quotations of first lines of a sermon have been included for those lacking a title. Most of the Yale and Riverside sermons were produced for public distribution, but many also include or only contain Coffin's edited manuscript version. Coffin's sermons tend to focus on social justice causes, including civil rights, the Vietnam War, homophobia, disarmament, and the Iranian Revolution, among many others. The sermons demonstrate the profound influence on Coffin of theologians like Reinhold Neibuhr and Paul Tillich. Speeches are arranged chronologically and consist mainly of Coffin's original manuscripts. Where known, the location of the speeech has been included in the finding aid.
  Writings by others are divided between essays and articles, sermons, and speeches. They are arranged alphabetically by last name within each of these headings.
  - Correspondence
    - General
      - 1943-1987 (Box 1, Folder 1 - 10)
      - 1988-1995, undated (Box 2, Folder 11 - 14)
    - Public opinion mail
      - Freedom ride, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - Iran, 1980 January-February (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - Vietnam
        - [anti-WSC], 1967 (Box 2, Folder 17 - 18)
        - 1968 (Box 2, Folder 19 - 22)
    - Unidentified foreign language correspondence [mainly Russian], 1946-1952, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Printed materials and clippings
    - 1918-1919, 1933, 1943, 1950, 1963-1985 (Box 3, Folder 24 - 31)
    - 1986-1995, undated (Box 4, Folder 32 - 39)
  - Topical
    - Abortion, 1984, undated (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Address cards, Undated (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - AIDS, 1985, 1991, undated (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - Americans for Reappraisal of Far Eastern Policy (ARFEP), 1965-1967 (Box 5, Folder 43 - 44)
    - Amnesty, 1973, undated (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - Bible
      - Bible studies, Undated (Box 5, Folder 46)
      - Mark [notes, sermons, and printed materials], Undated (Box 5, Folder 47)
      - Psalms [notes], 1980? (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - Boston 5 Trial
      - 25th anniversary, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 49)
      - Appeal [legal documents], 1968-1969 (Box 5, Folder 50 - 53)
      - Clippings
        - Magazine, 1968-1969 (Box 6, Folder 54 - 55)
        - Newspaper, 1968-1969 (Box 6, Folder 56)
      - Correspondence
        - General, 1968-1969 (Box 6, Folder 57)
        - Legal, 1968-1969 (Box 6, Folder 58)
      - Indictment [legal documents], 1968 (Box 6, Folder 59)
      - Legal Defense Fund, 1968-1969 (Box 6, Folder 60)
      - Legal documents, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 61)
      - Mitford, Jessica, 1969, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 62)
      - Press conference statement and jury composition, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 63)
      - Statement of support, Undated (Box 6, Folder 64)
      - Telegrams of congratulations, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 65)
      - Writings by others, 1968, undated (Box 6, Folder 66)
    - Budget policies, 1987-1992 (Box 6, Folder 67 - 68)
    - Capitol rotunda sit-in [legal documents], 1972 (Box 6, Folder 69)
    - Center on Budget and Policy Priorities, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 70)
    - Central America
      - Clippings and printed materials, 1965, 1980-1984, undated (Box 6, Folder 71)
      - El Salvador
        - General, 1984-1985 (Box 6, Folder 72 - 73)
        - National Agenda for Peace in El Salvador, 1989-1990, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 74 - 76)
      - Guatemala, Undated (Box 7, Folder 77)
      - Honduras, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 78)
      - Nicaragua
        - General, 1983-1987 (Box 7, Folder 79 - 80)
        - Printed materials and clippings, 1983-1987 (Box 7, Folder 81 - 83)
      - Panama, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 84)
    - Christianity and Crisis, board of directors, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 85)
    - Clergy and Laymen Concerned, 1967, 1969, 1986, undated (Box 7, Folder 86 - 87)
    - Coffin, Henry, 1937, undated (Box 7, Folder 88)
    - The Coffin Mission, 1975-1976 (Box 7, Folder 89)
    - Committee for Defense of the Rights of the People (CODEPU), 1985-1986 (Box 7, Folder 90)
    - Cuba, 1979, undated (Box 7, Folder 91)
    - Cummings, Richard [biographer of Al Lowenstein, lawsuit against], 1985 (Box 7, Folder 92)
    - Danforth Foundation, Underwood Fellowship, 1972-1973 (Box 8, Folder 93)
    - Death, 1983, undated (Box 8, Folder 94)
      See: Accession 2004-M-009, 1918-1996 Folder 510 See: Accession 2004-M-009, 1918-1996 Folder 520
    - Directors Summit, Washington, D.C., 1990 June 27 (Box 8, Folder 95)
    - Disarmament
      - Arms trade, 1946, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 96)
      - Clippings and printed materials, 1987-1991 (Box 8, Folder 97)
      - Nuclear, 1983-1987, undated (Box 8, Folder 98 - 99)
      - Writings, 1987-1991 (Box 8, Folder 100)
    - Education, 1987, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 101)
    - Environment, 1987-1993 (Box 8, Folder 102)
    - Eucharist [notes], Undated (Box 8, Folder 103)
    - Farming crisis in the United States, 1986-1987 (Box 8, Folder 104)
    - Financial
      - General
        - 1946, 1966-1987 (Box 8, Folder 105 - 107)
        - 1979-1986 (Box 9, Folder 108 - 111)
      - Speaking engagements [including correspondence and travel documents], 1979-1980 (Box 9, Folder 112)
    - Freedom Ride: clippings and printed materials, 1959-1962 (Box 9, Folder 113)
    - Gannett Center for Media Studies, 1987, undated (Box 9, Folder 114)
    - Healthbuilder, 1991-1992 (Box 9, Folder 115)
    - Homosexuality, 1977-1982 (Box 9, Folder 116)
    - Human rights, undated (Box 9, Folder 117)
    - Institute for Food and Development Policy, undated (Box 9, Folder 118)
    - Institute for World Order, board of directors, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 119)
    - International Center for Development Policy, 1990 April-May (Box 9, Folder 120)
    - Iran, 1979-1981 (Box 10, Folder 121)
    - Iran-Contra scandal, 1987 (Box 10, Folder 122)
    - Magruder, Jeb, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 123)
    - May Day, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 124)
    - Music [sheet music and hymns], 1977, undated (Box 10, Folder 125)
    - National Citizens' Review Commission on the FBI, undated (Box 10, Folder 126)
    - Native Americans [clippings], 1991 (Box 10, Folder 127)
    - New Directions, 1976-1977 (Box 10, Folder 128)
    - New Party, 1991-1992 (Box 10, Folder 129)
    - Racism [including notes for speech and speech entitled "Race Relations"], 1991, undated (Box 10, Folder 130)
    - Riverside Church
      - Administration, 1977, undated (Box 10, Folder 131)
      - "Biographical Data on William Sloane Coffin, Jr.", undated (Box 10, Folder 132)
      - "Conference in Solidarity with the Liberation Struggles of the Peoples of Southern Africa" [and related documents], 1981, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 133 - 134)
      - Disarmament program, 1984, 1986, undated (Box 10, Folder 135)
      - Fosdick, Henry Emerson centennial, 1947, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 136)
      - Guestbook, 1977-1987 (Box 10, Folder 137)
      - Notes, 1985-1986 (Box 10, Folder 138)
      - Olof Palme Memorial Ceremony, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 139)
      - Prayers, bulletin, and press release, 1962-1966, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 140)
      - Search for a new pastor [correspondence, clippings, and program from Coffin's installation], 1976-1977 (Box 11, Folder 141)
      - Second Fosdick Convocation on Preaching, 1982 October 18-21 (Box 11, Folder 142)
      - "Waging War in the Nuclear Age" [teach-in], 1987 (Box 11, Folder 143)
        See also: Accession 2004-M-056, 1916-2003 Folder 246
      - "Welcome Home Bill", 1984 (Box 11, Folder 144)
      - Worship bulletins, 1977-1986 (Box 11, Folder 145 - 149)
    - SANE/FREEZE
      - General, 1987-1989, 1992, undated (Box 12, Folder 150 - 152)
      - Clippings, 1987, undated (Box 12, Folder 153)
      - Coalition for Nuclear Disarmament, 1990 (Box 12, Folder 154)
      - Correspondence, 1987 (Box 12, Folder 155 - 157)
      - Third Annual National Conference, 1990 February (Box 12, Folder 158)
    - South Africa
      - Apartheid, 1987 (Box 12, Folder 159)
      - Clippings and reprints, 1986 (Box 12, Folder 160)
      - Divestment, 1986-1988 (Box 12, Folder 161)
      - "Free South Africa's Children" [symposium], 1987 (Box 12, Folder 162)
    - Soviet Union, 1986-1987 (Box 12, Folder 163)
    - Travel
      - Travel documents, 1969-1980, 1982, 1987-1988, undated (Box 13, Folder 164 - 165)
      - Trip itineraries, 1988-1993 (Box 13, Folder 166)
      - Trip to China, 1985 (Box 13, Folder 167)
      - Trip to Cuba, 1979 (Box 13, Folder 168)
      - Trip to Germany, 1983 (Box 13, Folder 169)
      - Trip to Iran, 1979 (Box 13, Folder 170)
      - Trip to Middle East, 1985 (Box 13, Folder 171)
      - Trip to South Africa for Desmond Tutu installation, 1986 (Box 13, Folder 172)
    - Union Theological Seminary
      - Board of directors materials, 1986-1987, 1990 (Box 13, Folder 173 - 177)
      - Printed materials, [1986], 1989-1991, undated (Box 13, Folder 178 - 180)
    - United Church of Christ formation, 1961, undated (Box 13, Folder 181)
    - United Nations Association of the United States of America, 1992 (Box 13, Folder 182)
    - Vietnam War
      - Clippings and printed materials, 1965-1973 (Box 14, Folder 183 - 185)
      - Correspondence regarding draft, 1968, undated (Box 14, Folder 186)
      - Reprints and writings by others, distributed by various Cornell University groups, 1965-1966 (Box 14, Folder 187 - 188)
      - Trip to Hanoi: photographs, [ca. 1972] (Box 14, Folder 189)
        See also: Accession 2004-M-056, 1916-2003 Folder 171
      - Writings by Coffin and others, 1967, undated (Box 14, Folder 190)
    - Vocation, 1991 (Box 14, Folder 191)
    - World hunger, 1974-1976, undated (Box 14, Folder 192)
    - World Policy Institute, 1987 (Box 14, Folder 193)
    - Worship/liturgy, 1972-1991, undated (Box 14, Folder 194)
    - Yale
      - Chaplaincy, 1946-1968, undated (Box 14, Folder 195)
      - Resignation [correspondence, clippings, and speech by another], 1975 (Box 14, Folder 196)
      - Visit of Russian Churchmen
        - Documents regarding the visit, 1956 (Box 14, Folder 197)
        - Photographs of visit, 1956 (Box 14, Folder 198 - 199)
    - Miscellaneous
      - General, 1968, 1977, 1991-1992, undated (Box 14, Folder 200)
      - Photographs [including carte d'élève of Catherine Coffin], 1938, 1956, undated (Box 14, Folder 201)
  - Writings
    - Books
      - The Courage to Live [draft of introduction and first chapter], [ca. 1982] (Box 15, Folder 202)
      - Living the Truth in a World of Illusions
        - "Fire or Fire", [1985] (Box 15, Folder 203)
        - "Mary and Jesus", [1985] (Box 15, Folder 204)
      - Once to Every Man
        - Complete drafts
          - Full draft, undated (Box 15, Folder 205 - 213)
          - "Draft with Harriet's notes", undated (Box 15, Folder 214 - 216)
          - "Draft with Harriet's notes", undated (Box 16, Folder 217 - 219)
        - Incomplete drafts
          - "1964", undated (Box 16, Folder 220)
          - "'65-'66-ARFEP", undated
          - "The Early Anti-War Movement" [portions], undated
          - "Conclusions", undated (Box 16, Folder 221)
          - "The Trial and the Appeal", undated (Box 16, Folder 222)
          - "Hanoi" [2 versions and additional portions of drafts], undated (Box 16, Folder 223 - 224)
          - "Peace Corps" [portion], undated (Box 16, Folder 225)
        - Topical [correspondence, clippings, miscellaneous], 1972, 1977 (Box 16, Folder 226)
      - Sermons
        - [Andover?]
          - [On the Hungarian Revolution], [1956] (Box 18, Folder 308)
          - "'Wonderful' Xmas", [1956 Dec] (Box 18, Folder 309)
        - [Williams]: Untitled, "To raise the question of fraternities is, I realize, to meddle with alumni loyalties and their intimate associations...", [circa 1957-1958?] (Box 18, Folder 310)
        - Yale years: Battell Chapel [unless otherwise noted]
          - Untitled, "The temptation, I imagine, for University preachers everywhere on the first Sunday of the academic year, as on the last Sunday, is to preach a "faith for our time" type sermon...", 1958 September 21 (Box 18, Folder 311)
          - Untitled, "Modern slang in many instances reflects the ancient Hebrew understanding of man...", 1958 November 2 (Box 18, Folder 312)
          - Untitled, "College vacations are often a little disappointing...", 1959 January 11 (Box 18, Folder 313)
          - "A Christian Understanding of Human Freedom and Anxiety", 1959 February 8 (Box 18, Folder 314)
          - Untitled, "One of the most misunderstood words in the Bible is the word, righteousness...", 1959 February 22 (Box 18, Folder 315)
          - Untitled, "Aware of the special festivities that mark this and next weekend, I have chosen for a text this morning the simple statement of the first creation story, 'Male and female created He them...'", 1959 March 1 (Box 18, Folder 316)
          - "Good Friday Meditation", 1959 March 27 (Box 18, Folder 317)
          - Untitled, "Even in the difficult stretch of human history through which we are now travelling, Easter almost inevitably is a joyous time...", 1959 March 29 (Box 18, Folder 318)
          - Untitled, "For the paratrooper who is at all esthetically inclined there is in the experience of jumping at night one perfectly glorious moment...", 1959 May 3 (Box 18, Folder 319)
          - Untitled, "Some 2600 years ago King Zedekiah of Judah climbed the ramparts of besieged Jerusalem...", 1961 February 12 (Box 19, Folder 320)